Register of the Štefan Osuský Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Štefan Osuský papers,
1901-1992
74065
Osuský, Štefan, b. 1889
126 manuscript boxes, 3 card file boxes, 4 oversize boxes (57 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, clippings, printed matter, memorabilia, and photographs, relating to Czechoslovak politics and diplomacy, and European diplomatic relations between the two world wars.
Administrative Information
Access
Box 120 closed. Use copies available.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (116 reels).
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1889 March 31 Born in Brezová pod Bradlom, Slovakia
1906 Emigrated to the United States
1908-1910 Studied theology in Springfield, Illinois
1914 Earned a Ph.D. degree in philosophy and psychology from the University of Chicago
1915 Received his law degree from the University of Chicago and opened his own practice in Chicago
1915 April Chaired a joint meeting of Chicago Czechs and Slovaks and engaged himself zealously in the movement for a Czechoslovak state
1915 September 23 Appointed Slovak Secretary at the first conference of the Slovak League in Cleveland
1916 February 22 Elected vice-president at a convocation of the Slovak League in Chicago, and was chosen along with Gustav Košík to travel to Europe in order to influence the Czech National Council established in Paris. Meeting with Edvard Beneš in Paris, Osuský succeeded in changing the organization's name to "National Czecho-Slovak Council"
1917-1918 Ran the Czechoslovak Information Office in Geneva, Switzerland, writing articles for the Allied press. Met with prominent figures in the national liberation movements, and dealt with German and Austrian agents like Heinrich Lammasch and Frederich Hertz
1918 September - 1921 January Czechoslovak Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to Great Britain
1919 January - 1920 Attended the Paris Peace Conference as Secretary General of the Czechoslovak Delegation, and became a Delegate a few months later. Negotiated and signed his country's peace treaties with Hungary, Bulgaria, and Turkey. Was one of the signers of the Treaty of Trianon negotiated between Hungary and the Allied Powers on June 4, 1920
1919 November - 1932 Czechoslovak representative in the Reparations Commission of the League of Nations. For a period of four years, also represented Greece, Poland, Romania, and Yugoslavia
1919-1937 Czechoslovak Delegate in the Assembly of the League of Nations
1921 January - 1940 June Czechoslovak Minister Plenipotentiary to France
1923-1937 Chairman of the Supervisory Commission of the League of Nations
1934 Awarded the Karlík Prize (the Czechoslovak equivalent of the Nobel prize) for "exceptional services rendered to Czechoslovakia"
1936-1939 Lectured at Charles University in Prague
1939 March 16 Refused to surrender the Czechoslovak Legation in Paris to the Germans after Hitler's occupation of Prague on March 15, 1939, and succeeded in maintaining his official position as Czechoslovak envoy, although bereft of both government and country
1939 October 2 Signed a treaty with the French Government regarding the formation/reconstruction of the Czechoslovak Army in France
1939 November 17 Appointed by Beneš to the newly formed Czechoslovak National Committee in Paris. Issued a mobilization order to Czechoslovak citizens residing in France, which resulted in the formation of two Czechoslovak infantry regiments (these, together with several hundred airmen, constituted a Czechoslovak army on French soil)
1940 June After the fall of France, Osuský arranged for the transportation to England of several thousands of those troops and fled to London
1940 July - 1942 March Minister of State of the Czechoslovak Government-in- Exile
1940 October 12 Appointed member of the State Council in London
1942 March 31 Removed from his post of Minister of State because of disagreements with Beneš's anti-Slovak and pro-Russian policies
1942 April 12 Resigned his post in the State Council
1942 Lectured at Oxford
1942-1945 Wrote numerous articles about Beneš and his Provisional Government
1943 Vice-president of the 'Never Again' Association
1945 September Moved to the United States
1945 September - 1946 Went on an extensive lecture tour of the United States
1946-1950 Visiting Professor of European Civilization and Culture at Colgate University, Hamilton, New York
1949-1960 Ran Mid-European Law Project of the National Committee for a Free Europe (reports on changes in communist states)
1949-1973 Engaged in anti-communist movement activities Broadcast for Radio Free Europe and Voice of America
1949 February Co-founder and Chairman (later President) of the Council of Free Czechoslovakia
1950-1962 Advisor, National Committee for a Free Europe
1952-1973 Member, International Commission of Jurists
1952 November? Founder of the Council of Free Jurists from Countries Behind the Iron Curtain
1954? Founding member, Association of Captive European Nations Member, International Association of Democratic Lawyers Chairman, Council of Europe - European Political Community
1968 February 1921 Judge, Court of World Public Opinion - International Communism on Trial
1973 September 27 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The Štefan Osuský papers were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives from his wife and son over a period of several years. The collection was organized shortly after the first installment arrived in 1974. The last increment was given to the Archives in November 1986, at which time the entire collection was processed anew. The present register incorporates material from the original register as well as the rest of the documents that were added to the collection since then.
The bulk of the collection consists of Osuský's correspondence, speeches and writings, and research notes, as well as of various documents and materials pertaining to Osuský's long career and activity in the anti-communist movement, to Czechoslovakia since World War I, the Czechoslovak government-in-exile during World War II, and post-war émigré affairs.
Of great importance are Osuský's papers disputing the constitution of the Czechoslovak provisional government in London, Beneš's constitutional presidency, and the role of the State Council (see, in the speeches and writings file, "Londýnské štátné zriadenie," "Dr. Beneš's Authoritative Regime," "Beneš's Government in London," "Legal Position of Dr. Beneš, of the Šrámek Government and the Czechoslovak State Council," "Řízená demokracie při práci"). In his paper "Continuité de l'état tchéchoslovaque," Osuský explains his theory of the continuity of the Czechoslovak state based on the recognition of the Czechoslovak National Committee by the French government.
Also interesting in that series are Osuský's writings on Beneš himself, in which he criticizes Beneš's 'modus operandi,' his anti-Slovak and pro-Russian policies, and his role in the Munich events that led to the subsequent dismemberment of Czechoslovakia (see, in particular, "Beneš a pravda," "Beneš and Commitment," "Beneš Manipulator," "Benešová vláda a Slováci," "Osuský Notes on Munich," "The Collapse of Czechoslovakia: Events Leading to the Munich Agreement").
Of special note are also Osuský's numerous writings on Germany, Russia, the Soviet Union, namely "Encirclement of the 'Capitalist Countries' by the Soviets," "Peaceful Co-Existence," "Communist Law and the Soviet Federation of Nations," "Rule of Law Under Communist Regimes," as well as his essays on Europe, Hitler, Stalin, etc.
Also of significant importance are documents relating to the beginning of the Czechoslovak exile movement in 1939 and 1940, in particular, Osuský's negotiations with the French government officials, which resulted in October of 1939 in the signing of a treaty relating to the reconstruction of the Czechoslovak Army in France, and to the creation of the Czechoslovak National Committee in Paris (see in the career file the original of the agreement "Accord relatif à la reconstitution en France de l'armée tchéchoslovaque").
In the biographical file are also included legal documents relating to the lawsuits brought by Osuský against Hubert Ripka and Bohuslav Beneš, which demonstrate, among other things, the lack of ability of the Czechoslovak émigré community to stop engaging in bitter personal fights and start to unify and coordinate the activities of Czechoslovak exiles.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); Prisoners of war.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Czechoslovakia.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--France.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Czechoslovakia--Politics and government.; France.; France--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; Great Britain.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; League of Nations.
Occupations
Diplomats--Czechoslovakia.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1915-1973. (Box 1-10)
  Biographical information, certificates, correspondence, financial papers, lists, court transcripts, obituaries, clippings, and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Addresses. (Folder 1: 1)
    Includes various lists of names
  - Appointment books, 1940-1944 (Folder 1: 2-3)
  - Articles, clippings, and speeches about Osuský
    - General (Folder 1: 4-7)
    - Kalvoda, Josef, "Případ Dra Štefana Osuského" (Folder 1: 8)
    - Valéry, Paul, "Štefan Osuský" (Folder 1: 9)
  - Bibliographies of Osuský's writings (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Biographical sketches (Folder 2: 2)
  - Calling cards (Folder 2: 3-4)
  - Certificates (Folder 2: 5)
  - Drawing of Osuský by Vlastimil Hofman (Folder 2: 6)
  - Family correspondence, including with Pavla Osuská, wife, and Judith, Paulina, and Štefan, children (Folder 2: 7-11)
  - Financial records. (Box 3)
    Includes some correspondence
    - Bank statements
      - National Provincial Bank and Barclays Bank Limited (Folder 3: 1)
      - Pozemková Banka v Praze (Folder 3: 2)
    - Bills, receipts, and invoices (Folder 3: 3-8)
    - Check stubs (Folder 3: 9-10)
  - Honorary memberships (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Insurance records (Folder 4: 2)
  - Obituaries, 1973 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Passports (Folder 4: 4-5)
  - Rental records (Folder 4: 6)
  - Subject file (Box 5)
    - Academic activities.
      Consists mostly of correspondence
      - 1936 November - 1938 December. Invitations to lecture from different Czech and Slovak student unions and organizations (Folder 5: 1)
      - 1941 - Cambridge University. Lectures on the League of Nations, decomposition of Europe, Hitler, Russia, the Allied Powers, and the end of the old world (Folder 5: 2)
      - 1945-1946 - Lecture tour of the United States on invitation of the Institute of International Education (Folder 5: 3-4)
      - 1946-1950 - Colgate University - Readings in Philosophy of History. Lectures and preparatory notes. (Box-folder 6: 1-5)
        Includes an outline of the course and student test results
      - 1947-1968 - Lectures at different universities in the United States and Canada (Box-folder 7: 1-6)
      - 1947-1968 - Lectures at different universities in the United States and Canada (Box-folder 8: 1-8)
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 8: 9)
    - Birthday, 65th (Folder 9: 1)
    - Birthday, 80th. (Folder 9: 2)
      Cards and congratulatory letters and messages
    - Communist campaign against Osuský in 1939. (Folder 9: 3)
      Note by Osuský
    - Dismissal by Beneš, 1942 March 31 (Folder 9: 4)
    - Karlík Prize (Folder 9: 5)
    - Lawsuits brought by Osuský
      - Against Bohuš Beneš and another, 1943 October 13
        - Correspondence with lawyers, 1942 (Folder 9: 6)
        - Court proceedings (Folder 9: 7)
        - Notes by Osuský (Folder 9: 8)
      - Against New Yorský Denník, H. Ripka, A. Valuchek, L. Šturc, J. Papánek, A. Ostrochovský, 1955 January 19 (Box 10)
        - Articles and clippings (Folder 10: 1-3)
        - Correspondence with lawyers, 1954-1962 (Folder 10: 4-5)
        - Court proceedings (Folder 10: 6)
        - Notes by Osuský (Folder 10: 7)
    - Letter (in Slovak) and legal documents from the German government, relating to restitution for property confiscated from Osuský during World War II (Folder 10: 8)
    - Portraits of Osuský
      - Historical Collection of the League of Nations. (Folder 10: 9)
        Includes correspondence and a poster
      - University of Chicago Law School Class of 1915 graduates (Folder 10: 10)
- Correspondence, 1901-1974. (Box 11-31)
  Letters, notes, and telegrams, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - A (Folder 11: 1)
    - B (Folder 11: 2)
    - C (Folder 11: 3)
    - D (Folder 11: 4)
    - E (Folder 11: 5)
    - F (Folder 11: 6)
    - G (Folder 11: 7)
    - H (Folder 11: 8)
    - I (Folder 11: 9)
    - J (Folder 11: 10)
    - K (Folder 11: 11)
    - L (Folder 11: 12)
    - M (Folder 11: 13)
    - N (Folder 11: 14)
    - O (Folder 11: 15)
    - P (Folder 11: 16)
    - R (Folder 11: 17)
    - S (Folder 11: 18)
    - T (Folder 11: 19)
    - U (Folder 11: 20)
    - V (Folder 11: 21)
    - W (Folder 11: 22)
    - Z (Folder 11: 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 11: 24-25)
  - Unidentified, 1921-1965 (Folder 12: 1-2)
  - A. Ernster and Son, Tailors, 1940 (Folder 12: 3)
  - Abe, 1948 (Folder 12: 4)
  - Académie des Sciences Morales et Politiques (France), 1937-1957 (Folder 12: 5)
  - Académie Diplomatique Internationale, 1938-1953 (Folder 12: 6)
  - Académie Française, 1940 (Folder 12: 7)
  - L'Accueil Français, 1901 (Folder 12: 8)
  - Achard, Paul, 1939 (Folder 12: 9)
  - Aciéries Poldi (Alfredo Bauer), 1939-1940 (Folder 12: 10)
  - AGEFI Limited, 1939 (Folder 12: 11)
  - Agence Fournier, 1939 (Folder 12: 12)
  - Agence Havas, 1938-1939 (Folder 12: 13)
  - Agence Radio, 1938 (Folder 12: 14)
  - Aghion, Raoul, 1938 (Folder 12: 15)
  - L'Agourtine, 1939 (Folder 12: 16)
  - Agrarian Informations [sic] Bureau in London, 1948 (Folder 12: 17)
  - Albania. Consulate (Paris) (C. A. Chekrezi), 1938 (Folder 12: 18)
  - Albert, Girard, 1939 (Folder 12: 19)
  - Aldrich, Winthrop W., 1949-1952 (Folder 12: 20)
  - Alexinsky, G., 1938 (Folder 12: 21)
  - All Souls Universalists Church, 1948 (Folder 12: 22)
  - Alleon, Paul and Romain, 1938-1939 (Folder 12: 23)
  - Alliance for Liberation and Freedom in Czechoslovakia (Jednota za svobodu a demokracii v Československu), 1953. (Folder 12: 24)
    Includes original text of declaration of the ALFC
  - Alliance Française., See Allix, André
  - Alliance of Czechoslovak Exiles in Chicago, 1959 (Folder 12: 25)
  - Allied Circle, 1943-1958 (Folder 12: 26)
  - Allied Information Agency Ltd., 1950 (Folder 12: 27)
  - Allix, André (Université de Lyon), 1938-1942 (Folder 12: 28)
  - Amar, André, 1940 (Folder 12: 29)
  - Ambrus, J., 1939-1948 (Folder 12: 30)
  - Ambulance Chirurgicale (Dr. d'Allaines), 1939 (Folder 12: 31)
  - American China Policy Association, 1951 (Folder 12: 32)
  - The American Club of Paris (Henry W. Dunning), 1940 (Folder 12: 33)
  - American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees, Inc., 1959 (Folder 12: 34)
  - American Federation of Labor, 1948 (Folder 12: 35)
  - American Friends of the Captive Nations, n.d. (Folder 12: 36)
  - American Fund for Czechoslovak Refugees, Inc., 1949-1954 (Folder 12: 37)
  - American Fund for Free Jurists, Inc. 1956-1959 (Folder 12: 38)
  - American Management Association, Inc. (Lawrence A. Appley), 1948-1963 (Folder 12: 39)
  - American National Bank and Trust Company of Chicago (Morris E. Feiwell), 1947-1964 (Folder 12: 40)
  - American Red Cross, 1943 (Folder 12: 41)
  - Americké Listy, 1971 (Folder 12: 42)
  - Ames, Herbert B., Sir, 1948 (Folder 12: 43)
  - Les Amis de la France dans le Monde, 1939 (Folder 12: 44)
  - Les Amis du Livre Français, 1938 (Folder 12: 45)
  - Ancel, Jacques, 1939 (Folder 12: 46)
  - Andic, V. E., 1948 (Folder 12: 47)
  - Andrieu, Jean, 1940 (Folder 12: 48)
  - Aprato, M., 1939 (Folder 12: 49)
  - Archer, J. 1938 (Folder 12: 50)
  - Archevêché de Paris (Roger Beaussart), 1937-1940 (Folder 12: 51)
  - Archimbaud, Léon, 1939 (Folder 12: 52)
  - Argentina. Embajada (France) (M. A. Carcano), 1939 (Folder 12: 53)
  - Argentina. Embajada (Great Britain) (Tomas A. le Breton), 1940-1941 (Folder 12: 54)
  - Arias, Arnulfo, 1938 (Folder 12: 55)
  - Armbrusler, D. R., 1940 (Folder 12: 56)
  - Armory, M., 1937 (Folder 12: 57)
  - Army Language School (Monterey, California), 1950 (Folder 12: 58)
  - Arn, Edward F., 1953 (Folder 12: 59)
  - Aron, Franta, 1938 (Folder 12: 60)
  - L'art vivant, 1939 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - Asociatia Romanilor Liberi Din Statele Unite Ale Americei, 1953 (Folder 13: 2)
  - Associates for Anglo-American Understanding, 1943 (Folder 13: 3)
  - Association Amicale des Anciens Elèves de l'Institut National Agronomique, 1938 (Folder 13: 4)
  - Association Corporative des Etudiants en Droit, 1939 (Folder 13: 5)
  - Association d'Amitié Franco-Tchécoslovaque, 1939 (Folder 13: 6)
  - Association de la Presse Anglo-Américaine de Paris, 1938 (Folder 13: 7)
  - Association des Amis de la République Française, 1940 (Folder 13: 8)
  - Association des Cités-Jardins de France (Georges Benoîst-Lévy), 1939 (Folder 13: 9)
  - Association des Garibaldiens de l'Argonne Engagés Volontaires Italiens dans l'Armée Française (L. Di Lauro), 1939 (Folder 13: 10)
  - Association Franco-Pologne, 1940 (Folder 13: 11)
  - Association Internationale des Ecrivains pour la Défense de la Culture, 1939 (Folder 13: 12)
  - Association Parisienne des Anciens Combattants et Victimes de la Guerre, 1938 (Folder 13: 13)
  - Association Suisse pour la Société des Nations, 1938 (Folder 13: 14)
  - The Atlantic Foundation, 1943 (Folder 13: 15)
  - Atlantic Monthly, 1950 (Folder 13: 16)
  - Aubac, Stéphane, 1940-1944 (Folder 13: 17)
  - Aubert, Pierre, 1939 (Folder 13: 18)
  - Aubry, Octave, 1938 (Folder 13: 19)
  - Avileon, F., 1941 (Folder 13: 20)
  - Aymard, Camille, 1938 (Folder 13: 21)
  - Bail, Albert le, 1938 (Folder 13: 22)
  - Balachowsky-Petit, S., 1939 (Folder 13: 23)
  - Balaš, Ján, 1940 (Folder 13: 24)
  - Baláz, G., 1939 (Folder 13: 25)
  - Balinski, Jean, 1940 (Folder 13: 26)
  - Ballantyne, Clifford and Co., 1942-1945 (Folder 13: 27)
  - Balloy, Max, 1938 (Folder 13: 28)
  - Bansillon, A., 1940 (Folder 13: 29)
  - Barabas, Juris S., 1946-1948 (Folder 13: 30)
  - Barabas, Z., 1946-1948 (Folder 13: 31)
  - Barbier, André, 1954-1956 (Folder 13: 32)
  - Barker, Duckworth V., 1944 (Folder 13: 33)
  - Barker, Ernest, 1941 (Folder 13: 34)
  - Barker, G. M., 1939 (Folder 13: 35)
  - Barkey, Eric, 1941-1942 (Folder 13: 36)
  - Baroch, Karel, 1948 (Folder 13: 37)
  - Barth, Karl, 1941 (Folder 13: 38)
  - Barthalomew, Bertha, 1943 (Folder 13: 39)
  - Bartík, Josef, 1940 (Folder 13: 40)
  - Bartoš, Antonín, 1954 (Folder 13: 41)
  - Basch, Antonín, 1939 (Folder 13: 42)
  - Basch, Victor, 1940 (Folder 13: 43)
  - Baschet, Louis, 1938-1939 (Folder 13: 44)
  - Baschet, René, 1939 (Folder 13: 45)
  - Basilique du Sacré-Coeur, 1940 (Folder 13: 46)
  - Bassin, I., 1937 (Folder 13: 47)
  - Bassols, Narciso, 1939 (Folder 13: 48)
  - Bastid, Paul, n.d. (Folder 13: 49)
  - Baťa, Jan, 1937-1959 (Folder 13: 50)
  - Bate, Marie Finger, 1949-1954 (Folder 13: 51)
  - Bates-Batcheller, 1939 (Folder 13: 52)
  - Baudrillart, Alfred, 1939-1940 (Folder 13: 53)
  - Bauer, R., 1939 (Folder 13: 54)
  - Bauer, William, 1939 (Folder 13: 55)
  - Bauffremont, Duke of, 1938 (Folder 13: 56)
  - Baumal, F., 1940 (Folder 13: 57)
  - Baumal, Jean, 1938 (Folder 13: 58)
  - Baume, Renom de la, 1940 (Folder 13: 59)
  - Bavelier, Charles, 1939 (Folder 13: 60)
  - Bazili, Nikolai Aleksandrovich, 1938 (Folder 13: 61)
  - Beauvau-Craon, Prince de, 1940 (Folder 13: 62)
  - Bechyně, Rudolf, 1940 (Folder 13: 63)
  - Beck, Rolf, 1938 (Folder 13: 64)
  - Beer, Raymond, 1938 (Folder 13: 65)
  - Begouen, Count, 1938 (Folder 13: 66)
  - Behic, Erkin M., 1940 (Folder 13: 67)
  - Belgium. Ambassade (Great Britain), 1940-1941 (Folder 13: 68)
  - Belgium. Office Parlementaire Belge (London), 1943 (Folder 13: 69)
  - Beltran-Masses, F., 1939 (Folder 13: 70)
  - Benda, Karel, 1948-1949 (Folder 13: 71)
  - Beneš, Edvard, 1939-1942., See Career File/Czechoslovak Government-in-Exile/Political trial against Osuský
  - Beneš, Vladimír, 1937-1938 (Folder 13: 72)
  - Benjamin, 1940 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - Bennet, Lord, 1941 (Folder 14: 2)
  - Benoît, Raymond, 1939 (Folder 14: 3)
  - Beran, Rudolf, 1937-1938 (Folder 14: 4)
  - Bérard, Maurice, 1939 (Folder 14: 5)
  - Bérenger, Henry, 1938 (Folder 14: 6)
  - Bergmann, Karel, 1950 (Folder 14: 7)
  - Bernard, Gaston, 1939 (Folder 14: 8)
  - Bernstein, Henry, 1939 (Folder 14: 9)
  - Berr, Raymond, 1939 (Folder 14: 10)
  - Berthelot, C., 1938 (Folder 14: 11)
  - Berthelot, Madame, 1939 (Folder 14: 12)
  - Bertier, Georges, 1939 (Folder 14: 13)
  - Bertrand, Arthus, 1939 (Folder 14: 14)
  - Besnard, M., 1940 (Folder 14: 15)
  - Better, Alexander, 1937 (Folder 14: 16)
  - Betz, Maurice, 1938 (Folder 14: 17)
  - Bezdiková, Anna, 1940 (Folder 14: 18)
  - Bibesco, Antoine, 1938 (Folder 14: 19)
  - Bibliothèque de Documentation Internationale Contemporaine et Musée de la Grande Guerre, 1939 (Folder 14: 20)
  - Bicanic, R., 1943 (Folder 14: 21)
  - Biddle, Anthony, 1941-1943 (Folder 14: 22)
  - Bielski, Boleslas, 1938 (Folder 14: 23)
  - Bigard, D., 1940 (Folder 14: 24)
  - Biographical Encyclopedia of the World, 1945 (Folder 14: 25)
  - Biskupský Úrad (Bishop's Office), Bratislava, 1938 (Folder 14: 26)
  - Bisson, Isabel, 1945 (Folder 14: 27)
  - Blair, Edwin Foster, 1947-1954 (Folder 14: 28)
  - Blanc, M., 1939 (Folder 14: 29)
  - Blattner, H., 1956 (Folder 14: 30)
  - Blažek, Karel, 1955 (Folder 14: 31)
  - Blažek, Otakar, 1937 (Folder 14: 32)
  - Bloch-Bauer, Ferdinand, 1939 (Folder 14: 33)
  - Blondel, Georges, 1938 (Folder 14: 34)
  - Blum, Léon, 1938 (Folder 14: 35)
  - Blumel, André, 1939 (Folder 14: 36)
  - Blumenthal, Georges, 1939 (Folder 14: 37)
  - Bochet, Lucien, 1938-1939 (Folder 14: 38)
  - Bocinos, M., 1940 (Folder 14: 39)
  - Boegner, Etienne, 1947 (Folder 14: 40)
  - Boegner, Marc, 1939-1940 (Folder 14: 41)
  - Boes, Lucien, 1938 (Folder 14: 42)
  - Boháček, František, 1938 (Folder 14: 43)
  - Bohmer, Alois, 1948-1949 (Folder 14: 44)
  - Bohunický, Matuš, 1940 (Folder 14: 45)
  - Boillot, F., 1941 (Folder 14: 46)
  - Boklund, E. G., 1939 (Folder 14: 47)
  - Bolander, C. A., 1939 (Folder 14: 48)
  - Bollack, R., 1939 (Folder 14: 49)
  - Bollaert, M., 1938-1939 (Folder 14: 50)
  - Bolle, Jean-Marcel, 1939 (Folder 14: 51)
  - Bondeville, Emmanuel, 1940 (Folder 14: 52)
  - Bonnein, Henri, 1938 (Folder 14: 53)
  - Bonnet, Georges, 1939 (Folder 14: 54)
  - Borel, Emile, 1938 (Folder 14: 55)
  - Borromée, Henri, 1940 (Folder 14: 56)